hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I your host
darus parvey Wayne and today I
absolutely thrilled to be speaking with
Professor Chris FFF Chris is a
neuropsychologist and a Pioneer in the
application of brain Imaging to the
study of mental processes he has
contributed more than 500 papers to
peer-reviewed Scientific journals and is
known especially for his work on agency
schizophrenia and social cognition
within this latter he has worked extens
extensively with his wife Professor
utaff together they have published
seminal papers on theory of mind and
social signaling and last year they
published the book what makes us social
again it is no overstatement to say that
Chris possesses a legendary status in
the Spheres of Psychology and
Neuroscience and so it is a real Honor
on my part to be chatting to him today
Chris thank you so much for joining me
and welcome to the show oh thanks for
those nice words you're welcome uh it's
are you are you in London currently it's
a beautiful day yes
all be a bit Frosty yeah uh excellent so
as I mentioned in my introduction uh you
root many or you ground many of our
social capacities in mentalizing which
requires theory of mind now some of our
audience might not we we our audience is
diverse you know act brings in people
from maths physics all sorts they might
not have a psychology background so they
might not be aware of what mentalizing
or theory of Mind actually is so it
might be worth just setting the stage
and giving a brief exposition of what
those terms mean if possible right oh
yes theory of mind is a rather
misleading
phrase
because it's not a theory of how the
mind works and it's probably not even a
theory so mentalizing is a slightly
better term I think but the idea is
that
a one way into this is to say we're
trying to predict prct is useful to be
able to predict what people are going to
do and to understand why they're doing
it
and theory of Mind originally said
people do things because of their hidden
mental state such as beliefs and
intentions
so if somebody takes an umbrella with
them this doesn't mean that it's raining
it means that they believe it is
reigning or is going to rain and the key
um
to the experiments on people's ability
to understand these hidden mental States
is the impact of false beliefs
because if somebody if you know it's not
raining and this person goes out with an
umbrella then you can say he has a false
belief that it's going to rain and his
belief is different from mine and I have
to take this into account when I predict
what he is going to do so that's
basically what mentalizing is about
that's the process of predicting what
other people's mental states are and
mental States meaning things like
intentions beliefs and desires and we
think that this is probably different
from understanding people's emotions
yes I can imagine a lot of people make
that conflation um I guess and a further
thing to unpack there is when people
hear about sort of mentalizing they
might think of autism and and the
associated difficulties in mentalizing
that seem to be associated with autism
but over time uh many autistic people
use heuristics or tricks or social cues
to mentalize yes is there a difference
because behaviorally they might manifest
similarly and permit kind of harmonious
social interaction or is theory of mind
or mentalizing committed to saying that
uh those who are mentalizing actually
have a mental representation a kind of
recursive mental representation of what
the other part in this thinking
um well that's what I think I don't
think everybody agrees with that there
is I mean more recently there is
evidence that there are two
I mean depends on how you decide to talk
about it two levels of mentalizing
which some people say the low one is not
really mentalizing but that is to say
some sometimes called Behavior reading
um that you can solve many you can make
many of these predictions without
needing to know about other people's
mental States
and um this is and it's so all also
in some sense automatic so it happens
you don't have to think about it you
just
um know this is the right way to behave
next in in this interaction and in
relation to autism there's some
suggestion that it's this lower level
part that they find difficult and that
the her istics as you call them are in
fact something that we all use so
there's this there's this thing called
folk psychology
which is supposed to be inferior but I
think is actually very important which
is that we know this is the idea that
people do indeed behave because of their
beliefs and desires and that's how we
can predict and their behavior
and this is a cultural phenomena so in
different cultures you may have
different ideas about how folk
psychology works and in particular in um
there's some anthropological work on the
C in people who come from the Pacific
Rim which includes some Meers in Mexico
and Fiji and these various other places
where they there's a cultural
attitude that it's impossible to know
what other people's mental states are
and that you shouldn't bother to try and
in fact children are brought up not you
know you shouldn't be doing this sort of
thing you just look at their behavior
and it even extends to sort of
interesting semi-legal situations where
in the west we're very concerned that
you know it's the intention that counts
not it's more important the intention is
more important than the outcome whereas
in these other cultures the outcome is
all that matters and even if it's an
accident you'll be punished interesting
there's an interesting level of I think
cultural effects on some of these
mentalizing stories yes philosophically
I certainly have issues with that but we
won't we won't go into that too
[clears throat] much um yes that's
interesting I guess because it also maps
onto our scientific institutions and our
way of actually viewing what's going on
mentally um EXA I can't help but notice
that we are presupposing mental
representations even when I asked that
question and I've been sort of delving
into the world of radical inactivist
cognition and they would say well there
are no representations there are there
is no content all we have are these
Dynamic relationships between or these
Dynamic couplings uh between agent and
Arena right does that is that does
theory of Mind collapse if we just
permit that these are um I guess they
talk about sort of perceiving
correlations in the environment that's
something that they're very excited
about but actually this isn't a in you
know this isn't necessarily a
representation or intentional stance
um does it does it is it compatible with
these sort of ramped up versions of an
activist cognition
hello everyone and I do apologize for
interrupting the flow of the
conversation with Chris I wanted to add
this little bit because I realized uh
upon watching the conversation that I
had with Chris that this juncture I did
misspeak and misconstrue and
overgeneralize the claims of wreck at
least explicated by hat and Mayan so I
made it out as if uh they say that all
cognition invol uh is contentless this
is not actually what they say they say
that basic mind or basic cognition is
contentless whereby basic cognition
means all cognitive activities except
those involving public Language and
Cultural symbol systems so again they do
not say that all cognition is
contentless because they because there
are also these higher order forms of
cognition which might be content
involving and again those require public
symbols social practices of symbolic uh
communication so they're therefore
governed by semantic norms and these
correctness conditions so where the
theory of mind is that uh that higher
order form or lower order form I guess
is for you to decide but you'll see
later on I speak about these kind of
scaffolded uh developmental capacities
which might involve content as if it
wasn't part of the theory of heart to
mind but it is so I really wanted to
clarify that before this goes uh before
this podcast goes live again uh just
more broadly I do want to take
responsibility as your podcast host for
saying things are accurate and truthful
and owning up I make mistakes this was
one of those uh places I would have
edited out but it really would have
messed up the flow of the conversation
so I thought it was easier for me to
just come on here and clarify that I
made a mistake and hopefully uh yeah
clear up any confusion again um I don't
mind too much if I mess up describing
what I think because they're my thoughts
but I know that authors far more senior
than me have put a lot of time and a lot
of effort into their accounts and so
it'll be doing a diservice to them
disservice to you if I misconstrue or
misspeak when describing uh their for
and their writings so when I do this
again because you know In the Heat of
the Moment In the thir of the moment I
will make mistakes as I did here and
again it's just because these are live
conversation so I'm having to think on
my feet uh but when I do it again
because unfortunately I am fallible
please do tell me uh I will always look
out for it I'm happy that I spotted this
one but again I feel a very strong
responsibility to be as accurate as
possible so that relies on you as well
so please don't inform me for when I
make a mistake and I will not keep you
any longer because this is a cracking
conversation with Chris and I hope you
enjoy the rest of it
yeah I'm not very keen on these ramped
up versions um I would it's conceivable
that this might be useful way of looking
at the sort of automatic mentalizing
but I think the sort of cultural
um folk psychology story
very much depends on representations I
mean we almost we're talking about them
as it I mean yeah um
I can't there's a philosopher called
Davidson I can't remember precisely what
he said but it's all about applying you
know rational arguments to what we
believe are these mental States so
you're saying if he believes that the
chocolate is in the cupboard he will go
and look in the cupboard is the sort of
um philosophical approach to this yeah I
mean and that I think yeah [snorts] no
as you say I mean these are uh sort of
an activist cognition on steroids um
there of course people and I don't think
you would disagree with them that
recognize that if there are
representational schema those are built
off scaffolds that occur from social
cognition developmental psychology being
with others and I don't think you would
disagree with that and that is something
I want to touch upon um in terms of
self-modeling and self- perception but
yeah um actually I'll backtrack I don't
think they would say that uh cognition
is non-intentional just that it's non
contentful or non repesent ation um but
there are obviously quite severe
critiques of that and there probably are
representation as well as they make
clear in their works so now expanding
that out to away from dactic or not
dactic diadic interactions yeah into
broader social contexts
why going Beyond just the coupled Duo
why is theory of mind or mentalizing so
important just for social institutions
more broadly
well I I I I would claim that we don't
think that necessarily okay so we think
that
that some people seem to equate social
cognition with theory of mind right and
we do not sure okay let's clarify that
yeah so we think there are all sorts of
social cognitive processes that are not
to do with representing mental States or
whatever and many of those might be more
relevant to larger group interactions
and we talk about I mean what's and the
original paper that we wrote in 1999 I
think which is sort of starting of
social cognition we had mentalizing on
one side and we had miror neurons on the
other side because they had only
recently been confirmed
and um murans are all about how we can
imitate others and how we
get um what's the word contagion from
others so for example emotions are
contagious we tend to feel the emotions
that other people are expressing we tend
to do what other people do um we imitate
their actions
and one very important aspect of human
sociality is overimitation do you know
about yes I I I I've seen some of it in
sort of uh linguistic uh Innovation
where a language learner learning
another's language will overimitate and
so they'll be sort of uh uh they'll all
speak in RP for example even though no
one's spoken in RP since 1910
[gasps] yes but I'm as I've not thought
about it so much in that respect but
it's more to do with simple actions um
like shaking hands is and you have to do
it in the right way and the early
experiments where they had these um
puzzle boxes which you have to solve by
going through series of Maneuvers
and the trainer puts in a couple of
Maneuvers are not actually necessary to
open the box but the children all
imitate these as part of the that's the
overimitation bit so that they do them
even though they're not I see I see and
the interesting thing is that
chimpanzees don't
very interesting the idea is this is
we're imitating not to get to the reward
we're imitating to show that we are
doing it properly we are part of the
group we are the people who behave like
this and they're
yes yes so it's kind of in a sense
directed The what in active inference
terms kind of a higher a higher order
prior
yes no that's that's very interesting
yeah I mean um I guess to return to my
initial question yes I I recognize it
might be an overextension of theory mind
I didn't mean it in terms of everything
is Fe of mind that's clearly not the
case because then it would be sort of
serious cognitive overload if I was just
mentalizing everyone and everything and
it sounds borderline schizophrenic to be
thinking that you know my chair has
intentions but it seems to me that even
in making or or or acting to confirm
that higher order prior that I am like
you and so you're going to like me and
and and we're going to be able to
establish this recursive relationship I
need to have at the very fundament of
that a notion that you are an
intentional conscious agent which which
kind of seems to me to be a very
lowlevel form of theory of mind it might
be implicit in our interactions but that
still seems to be present
yes that's a very interesting idea um
one of the things that we've written
about is
sort of addressing this question how do
we know when we're want wanting to in
competitive situations
and
which usually means you're playing an
economic game
like hide and seek yeah um
you need to know what sort of agent
you're competing against sure
and um if it's a very you know it could
be a completely random agent that just
is biased so it's very easy to beat one
of those or it could be a simple
learning agent that depends on what's
you know the pattern reward in the past
and it's fairly easy to beat one of
those and the most difficult ones to
beat are the ones that are intentional
and are trying to predict what you're
going to do as well as at the same time
as you're trying to predict what they're
going to do like rock paper scissors or
or something like that yes and then
that's where you get into this in
infinite recursion where you say does he
have a representation of what I think
he's going to do next yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah
and um
what is interesting at least the little
bits of information I have it's very
difficult to work out that you're
competing against an intentional agent
from their behavior and therefore we
tend to depend on our prior if we think
it's intentional agent will behave in
such and such a way if we think it's not
we won't and there's this nice
experience John donzo's group in Paris
where he has people he has artificial AG
that can do recursive Tom
yeah and he has people playing against
them you know at various levels you can
have zero Tom one Tom two Tom and so on
in terms of recursion and if you tell
them they're playing against a one armed
Bandit
they assume that it's not intentional
and they lose
when the agent is functioning at two two
levels of recursion
even though they have several hundred
they think it's yes if they think it's a
person they will adopt the high level
strategy and of course this is
reasonable because this high level of
mentalizing is extremely cognitively
um demanding yes so you're going to
avoid going to that level if you can
yes and there's this nice and do you
know about the beauty contest game which
is a nice example of this
I don't
ah this is invented by Jean mayard KES
anyway the task is you're part of a
group
everybody has to produce a number
between one and 100
and the person who produces half the
mean
production will win
okay
and it ke Kane's call it a beauty
contest game because when you have to
say who is the most beautiful person
it's not who is the most beautiful
person but who people think is the most
beautiful person anyway the argument is
you know if if you think about what are
the other you have to think about what
are the other people going to do and you
think if they're completely stupid then
this will be a 50 will be the average
number and therefore you'll win with 25
if they're not completely stupid they
think it's going to be 25 therefore
you'll win with 12 and a half if you've
read about um Nash equilibrium you think
everybody is super rational and you're
say one so you always lose um and the
average I mean there have been huge
experiments on this in newspapers where
they get thousands of people to take
part and the average number level of
recursion is two and a half
interesting [snorts]
yes it has to be a cut off there has to
be a [clears throat] cut off this is
what they call I think car would call it
bounded rationality or something yes
yeah yeah well yes I guess it's also I
guess in some sense to do with the depth
of your temporal hierarchy yeah um
because each recursive step seems to me
at least to be kind of a an N plus one
in your kind of information space and so
you're just going to the next one and it
has to be an end at some point we can't
plan forever that's fascinating okay
that's fascinating yeah no that's that's
the other game I'm interested in is the
um stank Hunt game you know that yeah I
know the fact yeah yeah Y and that's
again seems to be recursive because if I
go to hunt STS I have to believe that
you're going to hunt STS and I have to
believe that you think that I'm going to
hunt STS
and it seems to me theistic there that
soles all this to say we are Cooperative
people
and I don't have to worry about this
yeah yeah a couple things come to mind
there I mean dennet as I'm sure you know
has this notion of an intentional stance
um you think that maps ontologically
onto our sort of priors in some sense
that we we start off with the notion
that things are intentional animate
conscious however you want to term it
and then we start pruning or is it the
other way I think I think it's the other
way around we want to start with the
idea that it's all very easy yes yeah
yes but but we do have I I think we have
a prayer that people are intentional
and and would that be and would we get
that evidence from the phenotype of
people so to speak so so if you have the
sim a similar body to me you move in a
similar way to me you speak in a similar
way to me that is evidence to confirm
that prior but I guess it has to be an
evolutionary prior quite a non
conceptual level because Evolution
doesn't work like that it's not going to
say if you've got if you're six foot
you're an agent right it's it needs to
be a little bit more subtle than that
yeah but certainly there's this um
somewhat discouraging work on ingroups
and out groups groups are considered to
be less intentional
gosh yes that's quite terrifying yeah
yeah yeah but that said I mean we do
have it makes me think of the Fus of
form facial area and the fact that that
certainly constitutes some kind of
perceptual prior at least yeah excellent
that's very good um I mean I was
listening to an interview with that you
and UA did with uh I think it was the
denter it would have been about a month
ago and I think I I just was listening
to the beginning and UTA I think it was
UT that we could consider cognition all
like entirely social cognition so all
cognition is social cognition it makes
me think my Master's feis was uh
exploring what's called social Baseline
Theory and I wonder what you thought
about it I'm not sure you're aware of
social Baseline Theory I'm not so this
is um a kind of the experimental work
for it started in of 2006 2007 and then
the theory was fleshed out sort of early
last decades this people like James
Cohen I think it's Cohen it might be
Cohen um Elizabeth Gross these are
people that the audience can search up
but the notion is is that the primary
ecological niche we find ourselves in is
social yes and so what that means is
that the human brain for adaptive
reasons expects social resources because
it and in doing so it that acts to
mitigate risk and also preserve energy
expenditure yes so what they then say in
white it's calledo social Baseline
theory is that being with others
constitutes a cognitive Baseline so that
when we actually put people in an fmri
scanner we get them to do a task alone
which is the standard in cognitive
psychology we're actually viewing them
as a deficit because they have to engage
in all of this self-regulation
self-regulatory processes that they
don't they would be doing to a lesser
degree if they were have trusted others
how does that sound to you as a a theory
oh I I I I love that I'm very sad that I
didn't know about it it's really it's
it's there's this really the really
beautiful experimental studies I think
the most famous one is that people will
perceive a hill to be less steep if
they're with someone else oh yeah
because they I think the perception in
some ways again this feeds into a
broader question about to what degree is
perception influenced by top- down
factors is it modular I mean I come from
active influence I'm saying no like it's
definitely influenced but I think notion
is a perceptual uh yeah a percept is
influenced by your notion of how much
effort it is going to be in some sense
the affordance
how much effort is going to be to
exploit that affordance so being with
others reduces that effort no I think
that I would entirely agree with that
and there's other experiments that we
did talk about in the book which I
didn't know how they relate to this and
I'm not sure whether the Baseline people
know about this about affordance this is
this business if you if you have a table
with mugs on it
you will you can show that
you will get when the mug appears as it
were if it's within your reach you will
get um motor activity in motor cortex
and there's a social version of this if
there's a second person sitting at the
table even a a mug that's out of your
reach but in his reach yeah Will
activate the motor system so that you're
treating this is sort of group
affordance it's I call it the wi mode
it's within our reach yeah and that
seems to happen automatically so that's
entirely consistent with this that is
that is wonderful I guess in some sense
from an active inference perspective
it's worth predicting others actions as
if they were our own because their
actions are so influential on on
personal outcomes but I was thinking
more it's like the monkey and the rake
we can use this person as a tool to get
yes yeah ah yes ah okay so mine was a
bit more generous I guess it was a
little bit more altruistic ah okay okay
cool yeah that's that that's that's an
interesting um that's an interesting
stance on it I guess
I mean the answer yeah a test of that
would be if the P other person sitting
at the table is your enemy
would would you then not get the
affordance from the things yeah has
someone done that experiment I don't
think so no worthwhile um an interesting
experiment thought experiment that I
think you've used and Carl has used is
let's say we're on some exoplanet and
it's just me yeah yeah
um I don't I I want to leave the
questions about agency and sense of self
for a bit because I do want to get there
that's kind of more my speciality the
work that I focus on is more to do of
self modeling but we say okay all
cognition is social cognition it's built
into us it's it's our Baseline we have
social priors
how what therefore what happens when we
start denying evidence for those priors
if I'm in the planet which was just n of
one and I guess are there differences
there for if that was always the case
versus I've just been plumped there and
I've and now I have a memory in some
sense of being a social creature which
is now being denied to me I think yes
there would be a huge difference um I
would say if you just dropped there I
mean it's a bit like being put
[clears throat] into um solitary
confinement I'm sure you will start
thinking about the past or making up
stories or about social interactions and
so on and I was thinking also your nice
point about being an MRI scanner all by
yourself I suspect what most people do
when they're an MRI scanner all by
myself thinking about what on Earth is
the experiment of doing this for sure I
think that when I get x-rays actually
I'm like why are they doing this with
the blocks of lead and stuff yes if
you'd never had social interactions I
would I would think you would be
well in the extreme I had a strange
interaction long ago with Kristoff cooch
talking about I was trying to talk about
you know what's the function of
Consciousness and I was putting the
argument it's all social
so my argument would be if you were
never had interaction with other people
you would not be conscious I think Cole
has a similar yeah St yes and what was
Kristoff's response to that
know Consciousness is in these special
neurons yeah yeah I don't think that
one's got very far uh sorry Kristoff
you're far more senior than me but I
don't think that one's got very far and
he lost that bet to David Charmers I
think he had to give him that case of
wine yeah so so [laughter] I think he
lost um well that's a really interesting
point let's let's go there then because
as I said this is really where I want to
go is this self-modeling
yeah and I'm thinking again this is
something that I've spoken to KL about
and I've heard Carl mention which is
that we need in some sense to be able to
infer the agency of others or their self
model to be able to apply to ourselves a
self model um there's a wonderful paper
I like shouting out papers here so that
people can go read and also just to give
credit where it's You by yakob Hoy um
and I think his last name is Michael I'm
not sure what his first name is and it's
called why does anybody have a self it's
anybody there two words and they talk
about sort of cultural imitation as
really being foundational to the
development of a sense of agency in the
sense I'm going to shape myself model on
what I see as kind of optimal a IC
behavior on the part of others so I
guess the question here is how necessary
is this capacity for inference of the
agentic state of another or the mental
states of another for our own formation
of agency and selfhood
I certainly think that selfhood depends
on interacting with others
though I think you could get quite a
long way without doing mentalizing it
could be based on Behavior yes okay
extent
um but I'm one of the things that we
quite talk about quite a lot in our book
is reputation
which is very important
economically I mean The Economist I mean
not um Adam Smith who invented econom
economics talked about he didn't call it
reputation he called I can't quite
remember the esteem with which other
people hold you in
was was more important than wealth and
what the main driving factor in human
behavior is to get the esteem of others
is to have a good reputation in other
words though sometimes money can be a
sort of n proxy for this sure and
they're all sorts of interesting
experiments on this because if you have
a good reputation then people will trust
you they will choose to work with you
and they will inv invest money in you
and all that sort of thing
and then that you have a very
interesting
um arms race
with the Free Riders because you want to
have a good reputation but you want to
cheat people at the same time and then
you have to that's why being being
anonymous is jly useful from this sort
of competitive situation because no one
you don't have a reputation that carries
with you and um and it seems to me the
reputation is an important aspect of the
self and of course the reputation is in
is not in you it's in the minds of
others [clears throat]
yes exactly but in some sense it then
gets transferred onto you I mean I think
it's quite classic literary Trope in
some sense I've mentioned Luigi pandelo
before I don't know why but he's come up
again here he's got a well very peculiar
book called unoo chento one no one
100,000 notion is is that these are
different ways of modeling oneself self
and what what he goes around doing in
this book is protagonist is he he goes
around trying to spot himself in mirrors
so that he can perceive himself um not
so he's trying to catch himself looking
at himself not as others would perceive
him but sort of in this raw moment of
self perception and he eventually
dissolves or goes a bit mental yeah it's
that's one thing that came up into mind
there's another far more folk or or
popular culture thing there's a very
interesting show on BB on the BBC right
now um called the traitors
uh which I highly recommend which is
it's about sort of 20 people in a castle
and three of them are traitors and 17 of
them are so-called faithfuls and they
have to kind of Guess Who's Who and if
the traitors stay in they win all the
money if the faithfuls stay in they win
all there's some trash reality element
to it but it's a very interesting
psychological recursive thing where
there's lots of triple quadruple
bluffing going on so that's really that
in in action and reputation yes plays a
very big role in trustworthiness and
you're watching that as the objective
sort of Godlike figure and saying well
how could you not see that this person
is so malign um but you're not there in
some sense okay that's that's
interesting I guess a further question I
had and this is actually something I
would love to explore personally um
because I don't think anyone's done that
much work on this um so I put this down
as a sort of thing that I might want to
explore in the PHD which is that we
seemingly have homogeneity in self-
modeling um so there are certain things
that just come out of the literature who
I'm thinking about people like Dan Dan
Harvey and Shan Gallagher and um yob
that it's in some way narrational in
some ways it's uh epistemic it's
somewhat coherent um again this goes all
the way back to like people like Derek
parfit um but it's and and that is
homogeneous across us I was do you think
that that is quite a thought I had is
that that's rooted in the fact that we
all engage in similar processes to
arrive at that self-modeling to arrive
at that self-conception namely
inference about others does that seem
reasonable
yes I'm not sure I mean I would have
thought that
there's a
I mean I'm not sure are you saying that
because of our in inherent individual
cognitive processes being similar to
others we arrive at the same end result
in some sense but it's a little bit more
specific in the sense that uh let's say
I'm a I'm a child and uh I watch my
parents enact
presumably agentic Behavior yeah my
model of agentic behavior therefore
starts to align with theirs yeah and
what I do is I in according to act of
inference I act in order to provide
evidence for that prior
and so you see this kind of um
convergence over time on a self model of
course there's going to be variety but
these core features are present
I would think that certainly has a role
but I think there's also a role for sort
of top down cultural effects so you're
told this is what agents how agents
behave right as I was saying you're told
I mean even the very simple level you're
told that people be you know when
people are if people are eating a lot it
means they're hungry I mean even at this
simple level our behavior is determined
by our desires is something that to some
extent is top down imposed but I was
thinking
you were mentioning all these various
people there's an interesting gayen
straon yep objects to this narrative
story yes he does in and I'm inclined to
I I think there are different individual
differences in this I have no idea I
don't have a plan I never had a plan for
my life as it were me neither yeah and I
I might be a quite different person next
week or and that was
yeah so so yeah Gay's critique is very
apt here um and here I guess he's he's
kind of actually criticizing dennet
because dennet is quite keen on talking
about the linguistic form of this
narrational sense of self yakob how's
got a similar point there which is that
maybe we can replace the word
narrational with it's it's not as catchy
but something like a predictive
coherence or hierarchical
constraints or something like that in
the sense that the higher levels of your
uh generative hierarchy are tracking
lower levels and so your preferences
right like I like ice cream is going to
dictate my behavior in the moment that
I'm more likely to go get ice cream and
that feeds back and forward right I
think that maybe we could just I don't
know what that term would be um but no I
think it's a reasonable critique cool
that that's interesting yeah let's um
let's go to Consciousness then because
it was something that you brought up um
so there were two quotes that I'll read
back to you if I may that you've said
and I'm curious about
what you think these are from papers I
haven't just I was a completely
different person then yeah yes yes yes
that's very yeah very Derek parfit there
are lots of you um in 1995 this is a
while ago in a very I like the title of
this paper Consciousness is for other
people you wrote the primary function of
Consciousness is to permit high level
interactions with other conscious beings
and then this is so that's about
function yeah and then in another paper
you wrote phenomenological Consciousness
is necessary for taking an intentional
stance towards other agents to do this
we have to be able to treat ourselves as
agents also I think we can just brack
off that second sentence yeah yeah
because we kind of touched upon that but
there's there's one point where it's
function is
interactions and the second one is
almost nature the necessity for uh
intent the the necessity for
Consciousness to take an intentional
stance I don't know which order you want
to take that in but it would be really
interesting to unpick both of those
[clears throat] well I think
we've taken that a bit further I start
with the first one that sure is so this
is this study on metacognition
with various people particularly Nick
Shay and Cecilia Hayes MH and the idea
is and it but it comes from originally
from our the work with bador which is
about people working together you know
this study I'm sure so people are
working together to detect a weak visual
signal
and we show that two people working
together and coming up with a consensus
answer are more accurate than the more
accurate person working on their own in
the right context at least and the
reason that this happens
is that they're able to tell each other
how confident they are in their in their
belief [snorts] and on a tri B all basis
you choose the answer of the more
confident person
so in other words it depends on them
telling each other about their
phenomenal state if you like
why
yeah I've come across as David charma's
parrot on many times in this in this
podcast and I'm going to do it again why
why is that necessarily the case so why
could it not ju why could it not just be
an offline computation whereby we have
two probability distributions that are
just done completely like offline
non-phenomenal they're just numbers um
and you know you have a higher order
agent or or one of them you know there's
just a there's just a algorithm if
choose the higher one and none of this
is done online why do the lights need to
be on um for that um for that successful
Interac the information has to get from
one mind to the other
yes
yes if if we presuppose that uh
well
what for adaptive behavior
in this example yeah yes
could that not be achieved also with
offline Minds I guess is my point could
that why do we need to invoke like
intentionality qualia subjectivity all
the fundamental tenants of Consciousness
yes I do I don't really quite understand
so CH so Charmers in 1995 speaks about
how you can give me a function of
Consciousness so whether it's uh like a
global workspace or whether it's binding
or whether it's this
and but you can never tell me about how
that function maps onto its phenomenal
nature and why that function couldn't
happen I think what's wrong with that is
he's talking about the individual brain
and I'm talking about interactions
between two people and the key thing of
the interaction is that they have to
communicate with each other in this case
confidence
yes but could we not have something like
an artificial agent which has Precision
which could be a proxy for confidence
and they're not conscious they just have
done some mathematical computations the
inverse entropy and this is my
confidence right based on like you could
have that with a large language model
for example
so you would have to have so your
argument be if you had two artificial
agents they could also get better than
one working on their own precisely in
this situation
yeah there you go that that would be my
contention not that I again that doesn't
discount
the that doesn't discount the putative
role of Consciousness it just discounts
or calls into question the necessity for
Consciousness I guess right
but I mean on the
on the basis of that sort of experiment
we went a bit further and started
talking about do we actually learn from
each other how to interpret the is in
the states that we have
um and again it becomes very in
intentional
and the in and I'm not sure if this is
relevant or not but when we talk to each
other about how confident we are we can
actually then you get in competitive
situations we can
express more confidence than is actually
justified
in order to
in this experiment was to become an
advisor so people would want to take
your advice because you seem to be more
confident about it there that seems yeah
yes my only concern I guess is that um
there are these interesting Works coming
out about sort of extended Trust In Mind
Robot interactions or mind artificial
agent interactions and if I have a
belief that even a robot is extremely
predictable and reliable and productive
I can offload um a lot of my capacities
to that robot and actually if we were in
this kind of task I could very happily
take its uh its interpretation of the
events or its position as my own and I
might receive great outcomes but I don't
need to invoke in that any
representational space within that robot
does that in some ways not call into
question even something like confidence
metacognition whatever it is again I'm
not I'm not calling into question the
fact that it might be this it's more the
necessity of it right um anyway it's an
interesting it's an interesting little
rabbit hole Consciousness does this
we've g into you know everyone I've had
on and we talk about Consciousness it it
leads into these rabbit holes um we had
an interesting discussion on Tuesday The
Institute of philosophy
because they're all obsessed with large
language models yes and they were
talking about
does it mean when you know does it
understand what it's saying
and it was interesting that they the
presenter was finishing up by saying is
there is meaning but it doesn't mean
what it says so basically they decided
that
to go the the prop you had to have
intentionality
right which large language models don't
currently have [clears throat] how much
of this is sort of rooted in um John SS
work Chinese room and sort of thing yeah
excellent yeah yeah yeah it's good I
like to see that 80s philosophy still
has its role um is what I was sort of
brought up on um excellent let's now
it's not a jump because I I think the
wonderful thing about your work is that
although it seems diverse they all sort
of trickle down in into these
fundamental questions of agency and
selford um I want to talk about
schizophrenia
yes um and maybe we can start with the a
very interesting symptom which is
delusions of control yes so you spoke uh
you wrote very extensively on delusions
of control so again people who are not
schizophrenic or don't have a
psychological psychiatric background
might not know what I mean by delusional
control so it might be worthwhile
starting there just outlining what that
phrase means
so this is where the patient says it is
not me
doing causing these actions there's some
external agent making me do these things
and they could be quite trivial things
like combing my hair or they could be
more
um dangerous things like attacking
people or something but the idea is
and this is interesting [clears throat]
because
there's a delusion
typically is considered to be a belief
so you can say that they believe
that external agents
are causing their actions
but it seems more likely and early
psychiatrists had more or less stated
this is it's not so much that I believe
that external agents are causing my
actions it's I feel as as if external
agents are causing my actions
it's not just a belief in the sort of
philosophical sens is something stronger
than that well that's interesting so it
goes beyond the propositional in some
sense and there is part of a whole flu
of symptoms called passivity phenomena
whereby you can say I'm it's not my
emotion
it's being implanted in me and the most
perplexing one of all they're not my
thoughts
yes I wanted I wanted to get to that
that that is which is De weird yeah very
weird very it might be worth um
distinguishing
the uh delusions of control from
something like an alien hand syndrome
just so people don't that's right might
be aware of this notion of a Wandering
hand so the alien hand syndrome is
typically caused by a brain lesion and
that's where the hand starts moving by
itself and the patient says I'm not
controlling it or I don't have control
over it it's doing these things that I
don't want it to do but typically the
patient doesn't really say there's some
alien force right making it do these
things and they try to stop it I mean
the classic Strange Love in the film
if you do [clears throat]
I I actually haven't seen that I know I
know I'm going to get shout to that in
the comments um no pet say is playing
amongst many other characters as Doctor
Strange Love who's an exi
Scientific Advisor in a wheelchair and
he keeps making these
well it seems to have some strange
overlap perhaps with Tourette's um I'm
working on again I don't come at me I'm
not saying they're the same but it seems
like that um I've come up with this term
called oppositional self-modeling which
is a one level of some prior a one sort
of lower level of generative hierarchy
you kind of you have a h habitual um
action policy so you'll just do it right
so there's got to be some part of your
motor Loop where you will move your hand
or you will do a tick but then you have
a higher conceptual level where you
really don't want to do it because you
aren't the type of agent that does tick
or does move your hand randomly so that
that's what I mean by sort of the
overlap there with Tourette's [snorts]
there's also utilization Behavior after
frontal lesions
where people make these habitual
responses situations where they
shouldn't they can no longer inhibit
them
okay interesting yes so in terms of
delusions of control perhaps you could
explain to people where the model that
you proposed um for where this might
come from at least some of the versions
of it in terms of the inverse modeling
and forward modeling yeah well I guess
it goes back to helmoltz who
noted that
when we move our eyes
obviously the image on the retina jumps
about but we don't perceive it jumping
about and the idea is that we use what
So-Cal coroller discharge
so that you can when you send the
message to move your eye you also send a
message to the visual system so saying
there's going to be movement now but
it's not caused by something happening
in the outside world it's due to my own
eye movement and that applies to all
sorts of movements
and [clears throat]
more recently particular say with Daniel
walit you have this idea of inverse and
forward models so it says when I move my
arm I actually have a forward model that
tells me what what where my arm is going
to be when the movement is finished and
what sort of Sensations are going to be
accompanying the movement and because I
can predict them I can discount them
yes so sort of sensory attenuation yeah
and um
this is the difference between a passive
movement and an an active movement so in
a passive movement when somebody else
moves my arm I feel all these Sensations
because there's no discounting and
that's why can't tickle yourself yes and
the idea was that in schizophrenia
perhaps something went wrong with this
system of control so it literally was
the case that when they moved their arm
it felt as if somebody else was moving
it
yes they
and we showed or Sarah Jane blore showed
that they could tickle themselves
oh really I didn't actually see I didn't
see that I'm aware of her work I know
you got you fre all did wonderful work
in this in this domain maybe it's worth
um unpicking exactly what that looks
like technically it's a shame that I
can't get up all of the nice diagrams
because there are some really nice
diagrams but it might be worth um
talking about so people might think um
okay I want to move my hand to grip this
mug yeah this I love Dante mug oddly
enough um because I'm a bit of a Dante
acolyte that's beside the point um and I
can just I I just know what motor action
to employ and I just do it yes I think
you term that I think that might be ter
the inverse problem
what why why is that why is that why is
that sort folk psychology notion
not possible for you know cognitive
creatures like us
as far as I understand it the inverse
problem is that whenever you
you have a goal of Your Action yeah
which is to reach that mug in the
appropriate way but there are an
infinite number of different ways in
which the movement could proceed and the
question is how do you decide which one
to use yes and there are various
arguments like do you minimize the
energy requirement mhm or the distance
or or I think
um
Daniel walut and I don't know whether he
still thinks this thinks what you
minimizes the endpoint error
there're all so that's the sort of
argument about and also there always
different muscles you can use and it's
all very complicated and luckily we
don't have to think about it we just do
it you but underlying there is something
underlying all that and certain kinds of
lesions you can becomes extremely
difficult to grasp things interesting so
so so there are potentially infinite
ways of uh choosing a suite of sensory
uh sorry motor movements to achieve a
goal so it's kind of computationally
intractable to find a unique sequence or
a singular sequence um however we can
predict the outcome of Ro sequences now
that's a different point yes that the
critical idea with the inverse model
is intractable to work out what you
what's the best thing to do but with the
forward model once you have given a set
of instructions You can predict
precisely where you're going to finish
up
okay excellent and so let's so that's so
we've got the inverse problem the
forward model now and if we then fold in
what's going to be another kind of
inverse type which is the efference copy
yeah what's the efference what's the
role of the efference copy here as far
as I understand the efference copy is
just a way of saying we can predict what
Sensations are going to arise from this
movement
and that's the the thing that enables
you to stop the image apparently moving
about because you're
you know what the movement is going to
be and if the outcome is the real
outcome matches the predicted outcome
and everything is fine yes but if it in
the case of schizophrenia
the prediction is wrong so it doesn't
match the outcome so we have to explain
this um prediction error
and one way of explaining the prediction
error is saying
somebody move my arm
I see and this and does this require us
in some ways to go to for insertion to
say that yeah action some way many
people believe that thought is thinking
is an an activity
this goes right back to Lura I think in
Russian psychology um but it's
philosophically becomes very complicated
because you can say um
you have to say I intended to have a
thought
yes and that's definitely the Buddhist
might have a problem with that if if
you're thinking about a problem you you
would have some idea of what sort of
outcome you want to have as you work
your way through this problem and so
they are there is room there for
um you know metacognitive
approach to thinking so you you could
certainly say this I have not succeeded
in my thinking task yes you say I think
I have a good even when you begin you
can say I have a good chance of
achieving this thinking task and I guess
might relate that to tip of the tongue
phenomena where you say I can't remember
at this moment but I'm pretty sure if I
try a bit harder I should get there
[gasps]
so these would be examples of putting
thinking into a sort of active framework
yes there are some very nice
metacognitive models actually or or meta
awareness models with an active
inference so um there's one by L SED
Smith 2021 which is very beautiful and
these really rich Bay graphs with these
hierarchical layers um how so I believe
there are I believe there's good
evidence that people with schizophrenia
do not have major problems in motor
control
how is this accounted for oh yes well
that's exactly right there's always a
schizophrenic whenever you come up with
a theory of schizophrenia
they should be much worse than they
actually are yeah yes yes but the um
they do have they have eye movement
abnormalities
sort of smooth Pursuit and things like
that which would be consistent with
failing to predict properly the
consequences of eye movements I there's
a there some nice experiments from
Germany
you can do strain how do this work you
can do experiments where you have to
track a moving Target
and this means that you your impression
is that the target stays in the middle
of your field of view and the background
moves
though it's the target that's moving and
the background is stationary and you can
so you obviously have to correct
for the
S of the moving background as it were
and you can measure how much how
successfully people make these
Corrections and schizophrenic patients
are less good at doing that so there are
some subtle F sure that you can see yes
interesting does this actually I I've
got one more question before we go to
delusions and hallucinations because I
sense those are slightly different yeah
um I mean this is in some sense a
delusional belief um so there's some
interesting stuff there's some very um
there's some very adjacent or or
actually overlapping work in active
inference uh about agency and it's it's
very much a offshoot of the uh
comparator models and what we've been
talking about so and and a lot of this
is actually now been focused on
depersonalization
yes so and idea I really like is comes
from George Dean he's got this idea of
an alistic control model and what that
means is that if I can predict the
sensory outcomes of my actions very
similar to what you were saying and I
get a sort of non prediction error right
I get the results that I expect I can
start to develop the inference that
there was there is an agent in my
generative model that does these things
right and what happens is so let's say
let's say now that that's an inference
and I need to keep providing evidence
for that inference to keep it high
Precision let's say now let's say I'm in
a a torture chamber this is an example
uh torture is a very reliable uh
producer of symptoms of
depersonalization right say I'm now
getting tortured I have a prior that I
am the type of agent that should be able
to uh do things in to confirm evidence
for my own uh model of the world but in
the torture situation I might have a
desired action but I'm not able to
actually conf do it and therefore
provide sensory evidence for it right
and so what you start seeing here is the
disentangling of that very inference
that there is some some agent uh at the
heart of my generative model does that
how does that sound to you does it sound
very much aligned with the way you would
think about agency
yes I no I think that's very interesting
um
I mean we there certainly I've been very
interested in the feeling of being in
control
and there experiments on that um and I
guess the torture situation is where
you're totally not in control
which we likely didn't normally
experience
yes um
I'm just trying to think
yes a lot this goe I mean it's a very
basing story that
the feeling in control of being in
control depends not only on the
intention to do something but also on
the outcome
yes exactly exactly yeah yeah I I've
been writing with car and others on
so-called flow States yeah uh flow sta
surfing rock climbing playing musical
instrument and there although you don't
have this Rich sense of self this
epistemic agent model this propositional
agent you do feel [clears throat] in
control yes exactly and that is exactly
as you say because you are you have this
like alignment between your the
predicted consequences of your action
and the actual sensory outcomes in this
very tight motor Loops
um and I think it it's worth folding in
this notion of inter receptive inference
as well so this is people like annel
Seth and Lisa Felman Barrett this notion
that at the very core what um Thomas
Metson go would call your minimal
phenomenal self
they've argued that this is rooted in
inter successful interceptive inference
yeah either through autonomic reflex or
eating right some actual volitional
action and I guess something else there
is that torture would also uh deny the
possibility for successful inter
receptive inference if I'm not getting
fed I am weakening
I'm I I am unable
that that prior that I need to have a
certain level of glucose is not going
anywhere
um so I think what happens there is that
the the the the agentic model itself
dissolves rather than the homeostatic
requirements yeah so there's there's
there's some really beautiful work being
done here um excellent
before we go on to delusions and
hallucinations uh um I wanted to ask I
so my my S for is into Psychiatry are
limited I I'm more Adept at cognitive
science but I did read over the summer
uh Rd Langs The Divided self
I was curious um he he he's famous for
sort of instituting a more I would say
empathetic
uh and understanding approach to
Psychiatry that these people are not
just crazy right but they are what we
would now say are actually Bas optimal
just confirming priors that don't really
correspond to what we would see as
adaptive Behavior I was just curious
about what your opinions are of whether
you have any of R Lang and what he puts
forward in the div divided self
[clears throat] I
I no I don't have a very high opinion of
R Lang but then this is mostly due to
interacting with other psychiatrists
um and I
I don't think I might have read The
Divided s but I don't think I did
the idea I mean putting it into that
basian story is quite interesting
because
that seems a very good idea that is to
say they have the wrong prize but
they're behaving I mean certainly all
the stuff on delusions yes is the
suggests that PE the original idea was
that they're irrational
yeah whatever that means whatever that
means and that in other words they are
not argu you know they're not
appropriately arguing from the evidence
and um all the experiments that ever
been done sh they're extremely rational
and they're probably more irrational
than other people and as you say it's
just that they start with the wrong
priers
yes there's something in basian modeling
called the complete class theorem which
is that any any action perception can be
cast as Bas optimal just given a certain
set of Prior they're slightly worrying
yeah
slightly worrying well but it accounts
for things um it accounts for all I mean
basically all phenomena because if you
speak to co well actually you wouldn't
go that far but you could cast it all as
this kind of variational basian
inference so it's all Bas optimal
everything is BAS optimal um but I guess
the the flip side of that the positive
side of that is that maybe it does
license a more humanistic approach to
psychiatric patients in so far as
there's this interesting argument I
don't know if it's an argument there's
an interesting point which is that maybe
something like this going slightly away
from schizophrenia but it's relevant
something like PTSD or uh OCD or general
anxiety disorder actually is could be
quite adaptive in a certain ecological
niche absolutely if I'm the war zone
being you know having hyper salience um
and being really you know having very
high Precision over the likelihood of
some sensory input and downweighting
priors like in you know arguably in PTSD
is actually really useful
um but it's just not adaptive in modern
you know calm London on leafy regions
Park so how do do you think in your
experience in Psychiatry this work has
altered the way that we view psychiatric
patients
yes I think it has um I mean in
psychiatry in reality of course it's
very difficult because there aren't
enough of them and there's no money and
they can't find any drugs that work but
I mean that's the how that really
operates but going back to slightly
earlier question people like
gosh got his name
there was the idea that the symptoms of
schizophrenia not understandable
which is in another you know they have
nothing to do with reality or our lives
and I guess one of my AIMS in the sort
of story story of delusionist control is
to say they are understandable
it literally does feel as if somebody
was moving my arm
and and how much would you say this has
come from your
it would you say that person yeah yeah
do do you sense that this um empathy
that you have in in the very literal
sense of empathy that you can that it's
understandable comes from direct work
you know directly working with these
people
oh to some extent yes I mean in the when
I was with the medical research Council
my lab soall MH was in the middle of the
acute psychiatric ward
so I was interacting with them every day
and it was quite good because they were
actually very bored so they would come
and knock on the door and say have you
got another experiment for me to do
yes I think I think uh that's where K
started was in psychiatric rotations
yeah yeah how how did you guys first
meet if I may ask was it at UCL no we
met at the um the psychotron unit at the
hsith hospital oh W
where we had a there was a
project
I think run by Peter little to basically
start scanning patients with
schizophrenia
to test various theories and I if I
remember rightly Carl was appointed
because he had the psychiatric
background
to work on this project and that was in
the very early days before we knew how
to analyze
brain Imaging data yes so he was given
the task of analyzing the brain Imaging
data and the rest is history as they say
yeah quite quite what was it like uh
what was your your most cited paper on
ever yeah is the uh statistical
parametric mapping yeah work that you
did again we're going a little bit off
piece but this is the beauty of this
podcast like you know we can go wherever
we want what was it like be again I
don't know how SPM works I don't know
how I'm not a brain scanner so maybe one
day um or voxal base morphometry or any
of these things but I'm just curious
about what it was like
no it was very exciting yeah
exciting and I think what was wonderful
about Carl is that I mean there lots of
other people doing Imaging for the first
time and they were tending to invent new
ways of analyzing the data yes whereas
Carl very sensibly said but there are
all these statistical paradigms already
there yeah these are what we should be
using and that's
yes I've always kind of wondered how
Carl knew about them in the first first
place
um but I I sense that your work on
uh forward modeling um should I I you
know I was reading I had the joy of
going not obviously through the entire
catalog of your works because that would
take me until next year but going
through a couple of them again and some
of them are sort of canonical I've read
them before um and it's what struck me
almost like reading Thomas metzinger
I've said this before about metzinger
how incredibly forward like in
retrospect it just seems like you're
speaking the same language as we're
saying what we're saying now in active
inference Landscapes not quite but
nearly not quite but well there's a lot
of overlap and it's incredibly
influential and I would say that for you
and uh Sarah Jane and someone like
Thomas metzinger it's it's really
remarkable
how um you know how much was how much
how how in conversation were you with
Carl when he was beginning to develop
the free energy no all the time we
shared an office oh nice so I have lots
of passive smoking experience [laughter]
[gasps]
oh yeah he he he does like a cigarette
fair enough I think he's I think he's
warranted one and um have you given much
thought I guess we are on the active
inference podcast so I ought to ask
something more specific
I know we we spoke before an email and
you said you know this is not directly
your line of work yeah but you were
around for when the 2010 paper was
released the 2009 paper was released uh
I think a free you know 2005 might be
the sort of Beginnings um what were your
kind of experiences around then and and
how did you contribute
well I'm not quite sure yes I Carl has
his habit of putting my name on papers
from time to time and I guess I
contribute to some extent by saying
we need more independent references or
something like that or or I sure
sometimes change the wording a bit and
know what I was particularly interested
is I was very keen and it really goes
right back to Richard Gregory and people
like that the the approach to perception
and the idea that we if our you know if
if there's a prediction error we have to
update our model world and I thought
that was very exciting and wrote about
that in my previous book and so I was
particularly excited with active
inference because that gave you the
other side of the picture and when we
get a prediction era we don't have to
update our model of the world we can
change the world instead isn't that
amazing [laughter] I thought that was
wonderful I know it is wonderful what
what are your thoughts so this is kind
of what if anyone's familiar this is
what we would call the low road to
active inference yeah this is predictive
coding uh Helm Holan perception and the
like and action as action as inference I
guess you could say yeah have you given
any thought to the so-called high road
and by that I mean dynamical stochastic
systems and no that's too difficult for
me I'm trying to learn the maths yeah
you're not wrong you're not wrong it is
rather tricky excellent um okay so I
said we would talk about hallucinations
and delusions I think delusions we've
somewhat touched upon which is kind of
this uh fixity of priors um that is not
allowing for updating but
I read you know I read kapur's work on
um sort of the dope aberant salience
model yeah I never thought that any of
this stuff really accounted for
hallucinations
where where where do you the best of
your knowledge do you think
hallucinations might come from well I I
with Paul fetch we read a paper which
we're basically saying there's no
fundamental difference between
hallucinations and delusions okay if you
take a basian approach yes yes because
the hallucinations are
it's just about perception rather than
beliefs but in both cases it's all about
whether you update and where the
evidence comes from but the thing you
have to remember about schizophrenia is
these hallucinations are predominantly
auditory
and they're predominantly hearing voices
and One symptom is soall thought br
podast or no yes you can you I hear my
thoughts as if they're being spoken
aloud
um and you can even have a sort of very
similar story with the forward model and
there's work on this so that when you
speak
you hear your own voice
but you suppress it
and there's some evidence that when
patients speak that again the
suppression system seems to go wrong in
relation to
speaking as well and you have inner
speech and all these sorts of things so
the one idea is that they're perceiving
their own inner speech as if it was
from an external source which is not
that far away from a delusion of control
yes I sometimes think
how
true is that if when one meditates for
example if one is doing vasna
um it does seem like those thoughts are
coming from not from you
so this might be looping back into our
sort of humanistic approach to
psychiatrist all so don't tell that to
your psychiatrist yeah yes yeah yeah
yeah yeah I won't I it's true
at least and and the B you know there's
this these very odd overlaps between
Buddhism and Psychiatry and ego death
and all of these kind of things do you
think that this this notion that selft
talk let's say let's stick with that
because it's very interesting is selft
talk
from a Buddhist from a very raw Buddhist
perspective that doesn't get off the
ground because there is no self
[laughter] these thoughts are just
popping into awareness yeah and it's
it's all process it's process ontology
it's not there's no substance there it's
it's coming and going it's just the
field of awareness so is it just an
Adaptive tool for us to presume or or
have this illusion that it's
self-generated
I guess that depends what you mean by
self-generated I mean well not
self-generated but it's what does selft
talk mean then that maybe that's
because it's yes I mean clearly it's not
I'm not intention intentionally saying
these things per say but I'm perceiving
them as belonging to me yes they're not
coming from outside is yeah sure but
what's in this in this way we have to
kind of ask well what is inside and
outside yeah so so well that's I mean
that's a common one I mean one quite
dominant theory of schizophrenia they've
lost the boundary between inside
[clears throat] and outside that's
really interesting they've lost their
Markov blanket yes if you yeah yes but I
guess I guess the reality is you never
lose a markup blanket I mean this to be
honest it it points to quite it points
to theoretical difficulties in Act of
inference which is something that's been
brought up in this podcast before and in
in other works which is where do you
even cast the markof blanket and what is
it to say that you have internal States
and external States really what those
actually mean um and I give credit to
Maxwell RAM for pointing this out to me
is that internal you can just say are
tracking and external are tracked
but that said you have someone like Andy
Clark who might say well in my tracking
mechanism I might have my telephone or
my notepad and then you have yob how and
says no no no the evidential boundary is
the mind and even the body is being
predicted yeah does any of those uh
dichotomies or debates inform something
like um what we've been talking about
selft talk and uh delusions of control
well selft talk inner speech people used
to call it yes
and that is and again the Russian
psychologists I mean voty I think but
and there's some evidence for this that
you know young children particularly
doing difficult tasks what we might call
frontal tasks you actually talk aloud I
must now do this and I must now do this
and this becomes internalized so you're
do that internally and I think for some
difficult tasks and things like mental
arithmetic there is indeed in the speech
which is being used to control
what you're doing interesting and um
some schizophrenic hallucinations
where the where they hear a voice
commenting on their action so now he's
going to do this and then he why is he
doing that and
it's all very weird what they but you
can see a sort of
thread coming through this I mean that's
what I would call selft talk
and self is not
important well I wonder whether there is
some uh some space for a predictive
model here yeah in so far as if we're
going to talk about what we meant by
self self-generated an agency we were
talking about uh deploying some
prediction and having in association
with that prediction uh not just I don't
just deploy an action policy I also uh
precise predictions about the sensory
outcomes I'm expecting to receive and
perhaps we can talk about selft talk in
a similar way which is that at the
Inception of my selft talk let's say I'm
predicting uh the Sens or sensory in uh
Speech marks consequences of an action
policy of saying this at t+ one yes and
then I receive that back and that seems
self-generated yeah yeah and I guess if
that mechanism itself is disrupted
through synaptic problems Precision
waiting problems
then that is not only just going to be
motor action but also mental action yeah
is that appropriate absolutely yeah
maybe I should be a psychiatrist mental
action is a good term yeah yeah mental
action is a very good term well I mean
all of this um it's it's kind of become
very clear to me that all
such a plethora of behavior in in active
inference is mental action I mean the
very deployment of precision uh um over
what now you know we're using these
basian graphs these So-Cal pom DP
schemes so you have your sensory
expectations your C Matrix your uh State
transitions your B Matrix these are
deploying precisions over those are all
mental actions yeah um so okay excellent
okay that's that's okay interesting okay
that's very that's very cool um I was
wondering so there's a uh I believe he
was a philosoph called Lou sass or maybe
he was a psychologist and he wrote a
book called madness and modernity he yes
was he more sort of modernism
it might be it might be it's been a
while since I read it yeah um well
please please educate me because I'm
yeah I mean I read it too but it was a
very long time ago um so I mean it's a
removal of sort of structures and Bas um
um standard procedures and yeah
stream stuff um and how does that feed
into schizophrenia schizoph is sort of
uh the iology of schizophrenia somewhat
linked to having an unstable lifestyle
um yes I mean there's an interest this
is very um
unlikely to be true but there's
interesting stuff on volatility
so with when the when the environment is
volatile you should have a faster
learning rate yes and I think that
somehow interacts with the dopamine
system
okay so you could and there is some
evidence that children brought up in
very volatile environments are more at
risk
and one wonders whether
and then you've got this doine aspect
coming in as well if we've got too much
damine so you get the
[clears throat]
there's that sort of story and modernism
in the sense is increasing the
volatility because you no longer rely on
um I see cultural
Givens you know
currently an interesting idea in
relation schizophrenia which is bringing
the cultural thing is that most of our
beliefs at this high level are
constrained by interactions with other
people and culture more generally and
you could argue that what's odd about
what the reason that schizophrenic
beliefs don't update is because they're
no longer constrained by this high level
cultural
if what other people say
ah so these are yes your work is all
coalescing exactly
that's cool that's nice yeah that's very
yes it's interesting isn't it because we
think of ourselves as these we live in a
rather individualistic Society where we
think of ourselves as these atomist IC
beings and we're not and we're not
that's terrifying um
good excellent so so the book came out
last year yes what's on the what's on
the horizon for Chris FFF boa FFF the
fffs
well um we're in our 80s now um you
wouldn't be able to tell [snorts]
um we haven't got a major project
in line um
we have a quite exciting interaction
with our friends in orus in Denmark yes
where they have uploaded all our papers
and are trying to construct a large
language model
interesting who we really are yeah
interesting
uh is this Andreas
well no it's in his his yeah yeah yeah
yeah because you have a you have a
partnership with him or is that still
Ono we visit every year yes yes
excellent he's great I think he might be
coming on um yes you should certainly
talk to him yeah no I'm extremely
interested in this work Chris This was
um this was a delight um it's been a
delight on my part to go back and read
uh your texts I mean I did finished my
Master's just background about myself in
case you didn't I finished my masters at
UCL in experimental psychology last year
and I would say sort of your presence
and K's presence sort of lingers in a
positive way not in a sort of ghoulish
way through the corridors um so thank
you y my pleasure it's been an absolute
pleasure all right excellent